#### **NEKESAH T. WAFULLAH**



P. O. Box 10812-00100 Nairobi, Kenya Cell: +254 [0] 722 688852 or +254 [0]736 688859

Email: tnwafullah@gmail.com

#### **PROFILE**

A skilled agriculture expert with extensive knowledge in project management, agricultural energy, various forms of fertilizer, their production, marketing and application regimes; business development management services; cross border fertilizer trade policies; seed production and marketing aspects; food safety advocacy, youth and women empowerment and volunteerism. I am adept at project planning and management as well as creating simple solutions to complex problems.

Languages: Fluent in English and Swahili.

**Regional countries covered:** Kenya, Zambia, Malawi, Tanzania, Rwanda, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), Uganda and Nigeria

### **EDUCATION**

#### University of Nairobi, Kenya, Class of 2017

M Sc. Agricultural and Applied Economics Major in Agricultural Trade and Policy and minor in Marketing and Project Management

Maseno University, Kenya, Class of 2006

BSc. Horticulture (Hons)

Loreto High School, Limuru, Class of 1999

Kenya Secondary Certificate of Education

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Sales and Business Development Manager, Village Industrial Power June 13<sup>th</sup> 2018- To date

- New business prospecting and market exploration acquisition
- Marketing campaigns
- Product development
- Closing Sales
- Customer service and relationship
- Customer product training
- Customer acquisition and retention

## Agricultural Economist, Business Management Services (BMS) and Projects Consultant November 13<sup>th</sup> 2017- To date

- Business Development Management services for Cropmasters Kenya Ltd
- Business planning and advisory services for North Rift Agritech Limited
- Sales and marketing services for MEA Limited
- Agricultural projects planning, management and reporting
- Crop management services
- Smallholder farmers and farmer group management
- · Agricultural value chain advisory services

## Business Development Manager OCP Africa- Kenya Subsidiary: Nairobi, Kenya June 20th 2016- November 8th 2017

- Identifying new business and partnerships
- Identifying and managing new product and project lines
- · Business intelligence reporting
- Corporate client management

#### Selected achievements

- Key corporate client accounts
- Project links and partnerships establishment

# Regional Brand Manager (East, Central, West and Southern Africa) MEA Ltd: Nairobi, Kenya October 2008- June 2016

- Leading production, sales and marketing of organic fertilizers
- Designing and executing marketing strategies by market segments
- Coordinating monitoring and evaluation of the product's market performance
- Product registration in COMESA countries

- Business partnership lead, evaluation and assessment
- Product trials, assessment and reporting
- Developing farmer training programs on fertilizer and inoculants application and use ☐ Leading the implementation of two innovative projects: o USAID's Feed the Future Project on legume inoculant use expansion among smallholder farmers in Western Kenya region
  - Inoculant production and marketing of legume inoculants in West Africa (Kaduna State, Nigeria)
  - Business partnership in Zambia on legume inoculant production and marketing of legume inoculants

#### Selected achievements

- Successful completion of the African Knowledge Transfer Partnership Project Technology transfer from University of Nairobi to MEA Limited (AKTP Success story in Africa, 2008-2010)
- Increased sales from \$1, 700 to \$200,000 in three years from year of commercialization of the legume inoculant. The projections increased three folds by 2016
- Successful legume inoculant registration in Tanzania, Zambia and Malawi and currently pending negotiation for a partnership in Nigeria.
- Successful USAID Project approval, installation, launch and implementation (Kenya)

# Volunteer, Business Development Officer, Afrique Consult: Nairobi, Kenya January 2007 – September 2008

- Assisting with designing and executing fundraising projects
- Providing customer relations and communications support
- Assisting with office administration roles such as documentation
- Attending various training sessions in Human Resource Management
- Conducting preliminary interviews

#### Selected achievements

- Increased clientele base
- Increased company network

# Volunteer Trainer of Trainers Taking IT Global Group: Together against Stigma Campaign (TASC) March 2008 - September 2008

 Training of trainers in volunteer management, HIV/ AIDS awareness and against stigma campaign and food rights.

#### Selected achievements

- Awareness creation among youth on HIV/AIDS and how to prevent stigma among affected and infected
- Increase youth volunteer under the volunteerism program

## Intern, National Seed Laboratory Kenya Plant Health Inspectorate Services [KEPHIS: Nakuru, Kenya

- Attaining practical experience in seed registration, seed purity analysis, seed germination tests and seed pathology tests.
- Obtaining exposure to seed variety testing and inspection processes.
- · Gained skills in quality control, pest and disease detection and survey.

### Society/ Association

### Society of Crop Agribusiness Advisors (SoCAA)

Role: Assistant Secretary General and member of Food Safety, Advocacy and inputs groups

#### OTHER SKILLS ACQUIRED THROUGH TRAINING

- 1. Multilingual for diversity Taking IT Global. Award: Best Student Overall (Summa cum laude)
- 2. Finance for non-financial managers Center for Finance and Project Management. (2<sup>nd</sup>-5<sup>th</sup> August 2009)
- 3. Negotiation skills British Council. (July 16th-17th, 2009)
- 4. Effective report writing British Council (April 8th -9th, 2009)
- 5. Training of Trainers British Council (June 10th-12<sup>th</sup>, 2009)
- 6. Introduction to project management, leadership and team building and presentation skills British Council.
- 7. ICT and entrepreneurship skills African Centre for Women in Information Communication and Technology [ACWICT] in collaboration with Microsoft and International Youth Foundation.
- 8. Volunteer Management Jitolee, Volunteer Services Overseas [VSO]

### **REFEREES**

Wambugu Wahome Country Sales Manager

MEA Limited

Tel: +254-733-714-911

Email: wahome@mea.co.ke

Prof. Nancy K. Karanja,

Department of Microbiology, LARMAT,

University of Nairobi

College of Agriculture and Veterinary Sciences

Cell: +254-722-472667

Email: nancy@uonbi.ac.ke

Anne Wanyonyi

Chief Executive Officer

Afrique Consult

Cell: +254-722-817262

Email: anne@afriqueconsult.com